Hello! Welcome back to our course. Today, we are going to talk about variables and vectors.
Alright, so variables store objects in R, and objects can have any
structure and class, and then we could perform operations on variables. For example, imagine that now I would like to define
variable A, and I would like to assign to A number 2, so basically we could do this arrow here.
And I would like to know the exponent of A, so I apply a function X to A.
Now, I would like to define the second variable, B. I would like to assign a number 3 to B.
And then, I would like to know the sum of A and B, so I just write A plus B, and this
gives me 5. We could also define a character variable, so basically here, you can see that I'm assigned to see "hello",
but C could be also used to create new vectors. So here you can see that I created a vector
by merging A and B, and you can see that the output here is just 2 and 3, because I merged two variables A and B.
Alright, so this is the first way to define vectors, but what are actually
vectors in R? So vectors are these data structures, equivalent to mathematical vectors.
And entries in vectors must be of the same type.
Numerical vectors support appropriate mathematical operations, and let us have a look at that.
So, for example, here, I would like to define the vector A,
and I'm just listing all elements in A. Now, I would like to also define a vector B, and then I would like to define it through
a range of values. So basically, I would like to have, in B, all the values from 1 to 3,
and then you can see that, indeed, once I type B, I have all the values from
1 to 3. Another way to define a vector, here I'm defining vector C, is to use this function seq().
Here, I'm defining the first value, 1, the last value, 3, and then by is a parameter which tells me the step size between the elements of this vector. Step size
here is one. Another way to define a vector is to use the function rep().
In the function rep(), I'm just telling R, I would like you to repeat
this number, 1.5. And how many times? Here, 3 times. So we have 1.5, 1.5, 1.5.
Now we could also define this character vector. So here, you can see that E is composed of characters.
H-a-l-l-o, hello. And then finally here, in f,
I created a vector, which has
elements, this character A, and numbers from 2 to 4. But what has happened here? You can see that, actually, two
to four were coerced to characters. Why? Because we said that, actually,
entries of the vector must be of the same type. Okay, we could also define vectors in a different way. We could create a random vector from a probability distribution.
And in R, to do that, we basically use this function r*,
so to have random numbers from normal distribution, we use rnorm(),
from Poisson distribution, we use rpois(), and from exponential distribution, we use
rexp(). So, usually, when working with random functions, you should set a seed
first, to be able to then reproduce exactly the same results. So basically, to be able to reproduce exactly the same
randomly generated numbers. As you can see, I'm setting a seed, set.seed1211.
And then I'm just defining this vector, which is now a vector
composed of three random variables, these random variables are distributed according to the normal distribution
with mean 0 and standard deviation 1. And similarly, we could use function d*(), p*(), and q*(),
to have a density distribution, or quantile functions from different distributions.
Alright, how can I access elements of a vector?
Basically, to access an element of a vector, I need to use brackets.
And basically, as you can see, if I define this vector A, and I would like to access the third element,
I write A[3], and then you can see that as an output, I have 1.
And indeed, that was the third element of my vector. So, element indexing in R starts from 1.
And here, as you can see, a negative index returns all elements but the indexed ones.
So, for example, here, if we follow up with our example:
Here in that bracket, I selected elements from 1 to 2, elements from 1 to 2 are these:
Number 2 and 3. And as an output, I have number 2 and 3.
And then, negative indexing. What do I have here? So basically, I'm telling R:
Give me all the elements, show me all the elements apart from the first and the third.
First element was 2, third element was 1. And what I can see, all the remaining elements, so 3 and 4
from that vector. So I don't want R here, once again, to show me elements 1 and 3.
All right. Now, once again, here we have this vector A, and then I would like to ask
R to tell me which of the elements inside
this vector are smaller than 3. And I can see that R told me that the first element is smaller,
the second is not. The third is smaller, and the fourth is not.
Now, I would like to also maybe ask R to tell me which indices
refer to these elements, which are indeed smaller. I could use a function:
which A < 3 gives me 1 and 3? Why? Because the element on the first position
and on the third position was smaller than 3. Now, which gives me the indices, but
if I would like to ask R, which are these numbers with the indices,
which are basically here, smaller than 3, what do I do? There are two ways to do it:
Here, I could do it through bracketing without the which function, so I'm telling R:
This is my vector A, and now A smaller than 3, you remember,
it gives us this vector with logical elements. And now, here
I just put A minus 3 to my bracket. And as an output, I have 2 and 1. So in this way, I can see which are these numbers, which are smaller than 3,
in vector A. Another way is to use directly a function which, so A,
and then, once again, which A smaller than 3, we know that which A smaller than 3.
Gives us an index. Of a number, or indices of numbers,
which are smaller than 3 in vector A, so basically I'm just asking R now in the bracket
to give me numbers with these indices defined through function which(),
and as you can see, the result is the same, it's 2 1, so basically
I can see the numbers in a vector A, which are smaller than 3.
All right, so now a little bit of vector algebra. Here, I'm defining these two new vectors, A and B.
They are defined through just listing the elements. And then I could definitely define
an operation on this vector. For example, I could divide that vector by 2. So A divided by 2, and I have exactly
all the elements divided by 2. I could multiply all the elements by 2, so here you can see all the elements multiplied by 2.
I could do element-wise multiplication, so if I have two vectors of the same length
and then, if I write A*B, then all the elements would be multiplied by
each other. I could define an inner product, so inner product, what do I have? So I have the first element of the first vector, the first element of the second vector
plus the second element of the first vector, the second element of the second vector,
plus, the third element of the first vector and the third element
of the second vector. So I have 1 plus 4 plus 9
and then this inner product gives me 14. We could also define an outer product, so outer product here.
What would it be? Basically, an outer product would be
this matrix, and then how is this matrix constructed?
So basically, on Ith Jth
Element of this matrix. We have Ith element of vector A
times Jth element of vector B. So, for example, here, what do we have? We have
I-J, so we have 1-1. So we have 1 times 1.
Here, we have the first vector is A, and the second vector is B. So we have
1 times 2. And then, here, we have 3, because we have 1 times 3, etc.
And now, we could also, transpose a vector, but please be mindful that
as a result, we would obtain a matrix. So we can see that if we transpose a vector, we obtain a matrix which is
1x3 dimensional. Alright, now a little bit more about basic functions:
For example, here, I'm setting the seed to be able to reproduce these results
and then I'm defining a vector X. And X is a vector composed of random variables from exponential distribution.
This is a vector which is 1,000 elements long, and this is just a rate parameter
for the exponential distribution. Alright if I would like to know the length of X, I could just apply function length(x).
If I would like to see the first elements of X, I could apply a function head(x).
So, head applied to X. And then here, I write how many first elements I would like to see. I would like to see two first elements, and I can see two first elements.
Now, I could also define a mean of X by using this function mean, mean of X here is given as follows.
There's also a medium function. We could also ask R to give us standard deviation, std of X.
And this is it. The output, we could also ask R to give us variance.
We could also ask R to give us minimum and maximum.
And if we ask R for a range, then actually we'll receive these two numbers together, bundled in a
vector. Alright, and now two other functions. So, actually 3 other functions. We have a
quantile function here, so a quantile function applied to a vector gives us,
quantiles we ask for, so I asked for 0.25 quantile and 0.75 quantile, and you can see that, indeed,
R, gives us as an output, these two quantiles.
Another function, interesting function, is a sort function. What does it do? If I sort my
vector, and then the default is decreasing falls, so basically, I sort vector elements in an increasing order,
what do I get? Basically, I obtain as an output
sorted elements. So basically, this is the smallest element of all the elements in this vector.
And this is the second smallest. Now, order
function, so if I apply order function on X, what does it give us?
Well, it gives us, actually, the index
of two smallest elements. What does it mean? So basically, here, these are two smallest elements.
And there, I have the index
of these two smallest elements from the original vector X here.
So how do I know this is exactly the case? Because now, if I access
these two elements in a vector X, I ask R: Hey, give me element 439
and 881, then I precisely see the same numbers. So these two elements
of vector X are the smallest elements, because
I know it already by using a function sort. Okay, and now let us briefly talk about missing values. So, missing values are inevitable
in data analysis, data science, etc. So here, I defined a vector
which contains just numbers, and then one missing variable.
Missing viable is denoted in R by this NA. NA stands for not available.
Okay, so now, what happens if I apply a function mean() to a vector which has one element,
which is NA. Well, I obtain NA. So, to adjust it,
what do I need to do? I need to tell R to compute a mean
on vector X. But I need to ask it to exclude
all missing elements. So here: na.rm, so remove NA, and then we have a mean
of all the remaining elements. Now, if I do a division by 0,
3 over 0. Here, I obtain infinity. Why? Because infinity is the limit of 3 over 0.
Now, if I apply some functions which are not defined mathematically, so for example, if I apply a function to log to minus 2,
what do I get? I get a warning. A warning that
not a number is produced, because that function is not defined for
negative values. Similarly, if I apply square root to minus 5,
I get an error, actually a warning. That not a number was produced, because once again, a square root is not defined.
for minus 5, but if I define the same function, if I ask R to give me a value of square root
of minus 5, plus a complex element, so square root is
defined for negative values on a complex space. Then, indeed, I don't get any warning. Alright, so let me stop here.
And then we are going to talk about lists and matrices.